{"tossups":[{"question":"In Electric Six’s song “Improper Dancing,” this word is followed by a musical representation of this word that, in live performances, is sometimes replaced by a different song entirely. A musical representation of this word precedes the line “there’s nothing you can do or say, baby” in “Stronger” by Britney Spears. A song that is titled for this word and that includes several musical representations of this word is the opening track of (*) Ritual de lo Habitual [reet-WALL day loh ah-beet-WALL] by Jane’s Addiction. In James Taylor’s version of “How Sweet It Is (To Be Loved by You),” a musical representation of this word precedes the phrase “thank you baby.” For 10 points, name this word that MC Hammer appropriately follows with a brief pause before he says “hammer time.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>stop<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>stop<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Physics","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"The North Yorkshire hill Roseberry Topping is likely named after this deity. Linguistically dubious comparisons involving place names in the Azov region inspired a project named for the “search for” this deity, carried out in the early 2000s. A genitive form of this deity’s name “Hár” appears in the title of a collection of gnomic poems preserved in the Codex (*) Regius. This deity’s name is etymologically related to that of a god of rage who is the father of Hnoss and husband of Freyja [FRAY-uh]. This god gives himself names meaning “High,” “Just-as-High,” and “Third” in the Gylfaginning [GOOl-vuh-GHIN-ing]. This god hangs himself from a tree for nine days and nights to gain knowledge of the runes. For 10 points, what Norse god is the origin of the word “Wednesday”?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Odin<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Woden<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>Wuotan<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>Odin<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Woden<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>Wuotan<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Mythology","subcategory":"Mythology","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"The use of this word in the subtitle of Luigi Chiarelli’s [kyah-REL-lee’s] play The Mask and the Face inspired the name of a theatrical genre. A popular theory states that this word originally described paintings found on the walls of Roman ruins like the Domus Aurea. Shortened forms of the word “erotic” and this word are combined to create the name of a Japanese genre characterized by nudity and gore. In (*) typography, this word is sometimes used as a synonym for “sans-serif.” Architectural features referred to by this word or the word “chimera” are often erroneously called “gargoyles.” For 10 points, name this word describing things that are unnatural or hideous, which in an artistic context was once used interchangeably with the similar “arabesque.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>grotesque<\/b><\/u> [accept theater of the <b><u>grotesque<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>grotesque<\/b><\/u> [accept theater of the <b><u>grotesque<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"Walter Cronkite once angered his show’s sponsor by refusing to say this word on the air. This is the closest English equivalent to the French particle genre [ZHAHN-ruh]. In an archaic usage, this word fills in the blank in the sentence “She [blanked] to have died,” meaning “She nearly died.” Grammar sticklers were annoyed by the use of this word as a subordinating conjunction in an ad campaign for (*) Winston cigarettes introduced in 1954. When used with contrastive focus reduplication, this word is a synonym for “fancy,” in the British sense of the verb “fancy.” The Canadian linguist Sali Tagliamonte has studied the quotative use of this word, in which it follows the verb “be” to introduce a quotation in casual speech. For 10 points, name this four-letter word which is used in many similes.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>like<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>like<\/b><\/u>","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"A novel by this author uses the word “alfear” to mean “uncontrollable fear caused by elves.” According to the title of a Ben Blatt book which statistically analyzes the work of canonical authors, this author’s favorite word is “mauve.” In a memoir, this author wrote that the unpronounceable string “k-z-s-p-y-g-v” represents a rainbow in a private alphabet, inspired by this author’s grapheme-color (*) synesthesia. An acrostic message mentioning the title characters, Cynthia and Sibyl, is spelled out in the last paragraph of this author’s story “The Vane Sisters.” This author of Speak, Memory used the phrase “the tip of the tongue taking a trip of three steps” to describe the three-syllable nickname of the “nymphet” Dolores Haze. For 10 points, name this author of Lolita.","formatted_answer":"Vladimir (Vladimirovich) <b><u>Nabokov<\/b><\/u> [or Vladimir <b><u>Sirin<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Vladimir (Vladimirovich) <b><u>Nabokov<\/b><\/u> [or Vladimir <b><u>Sirin<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"In The 25th Annual Putnam County Spelling Bee, Barfée [bar-FAY] hesitates over whether to spell this word correctly to win the bee, but decides to do so with Olive’s encouragement. In a Calvin and Hobbes strip, Hobbes notes that Calvin misspelled this word in the “artist’s statement” explaining his chalk art. Wilhelm Dilthey [VIL-helm DIL-tye] borrowed this word from a philosopher who used it to describe the power that allows us to “comprehend the infinite in the (*) world of sense” in a 1790 treatise on aesthetics. This word, which was first used in Kant’s Critique of Judgment, was borrowed into English, becoming one of the few words in the language with two consecutive U’s. For 10 points, the word “worldview” is a calque of what German word for a person’s conception of the world?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>weltanschauung<\/b><\/u> [VELT-on-SHAU-ung]","answer":"<b><u>weltanschauung<\/b><\/u> [VELT-on-SHAU-ung]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"A controversial phrase in this language meaning “absolute sovereignty” is represented by a black, white and red flag. A phrase in this language referring to an immersion-based language revitalization strategy was translated into English as “language nest.” A hill in the Hawke’s Bay region has an 85-letter name in this language that is the world’s longest single-word place name. This language’s 15-letter (*) alphabet includes the digraphs “N-G” and “W-H.” The greeting kia ora [KYOH-ruh] comes from this language. Winston Peters opposes the proposal to adopt this language’s word Aotearoa [ow-TEH-ah-roh-ah] as the official name for a country. For 10 points, the Treaty of Waitangi [wye-TONG-ee] is written in English and what indigenous language of New Zealand?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Māori<\/b><\/u> language [or Te <b><u>Reo<\/b><\/u> Māori]","answer":"<b><u>Māori<\/b><\/u> language [or Te <b><u>Reo<\/b><\/u> Māori]","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"The word “liff” is defined as a type of this object in The Meaning of Liff by Douglas Adams and John Lloyd. Many posts categorized as “riffs” appear on Edwin Turner’s blog, which is named for a word for someone who steals these objects. “Colporteur” is a quaint word for a seller of these objects. The adjective “midlist” is typically used to describe these objects. The Japanese word (*) tsundoku refers to the practice of hoarding these objects. The “block” type of these objects is an example of incunabula, which are objects of this kind produced before 1500. A colophon is an informative description of one of these objects, and often appears on the verso side of part of one of these objects. For 10 points, name these objects beloved by bibliophiles.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>book<\/b><\/u>s","answer":"<b><u>book<\/b><\/u>s","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"Arthur Guiterman noted that this property is possessed by the last name of the naval officer who moved Cleopatra’s Needle from Egypt to Central Park. This property is also possessed by an archaic name for the portion of a fungus or plant that produces spores. Talking cats and dogs frequently appear in a Hilary B. Price comic strip named after this property. On the song “Tone Deaf,” Eminem makes the dubious claim that he can make the word (*) “banana” have this property. Willard Espy and Tom Lehrer are among the writers who have used enjambment to achieve this famously uncommon property. For 10 points, in some dialects, the phrase “door hinge” has what rare property related to the word for a certain color?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>rhyme<\/b><\/u>s with <b><u>orange<\/b><\/u> (Henry Honychurch Gorringe was the officer who moved Cleopatra’s Needle.)","answer":"<b><u>rhyme<\/b><\/u>s with <b><u>orange<\/b><\/u> (Henry Honychurch Gorringe was the officer who moved Cleopatra’s Needle.)","category":"Trash","subcategory":"Trash","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"This composer used contrary formulae to represent the words “have” and “be” in a system that uses the German musical alphabet to translate the nouns, adjectives, and verbs in the Summa Theologica into musical form. This composer wrote “Jesus is considered here as the Word” to describe a movement marked “infinitely slow, ecstatic,” for piano and cello. This composer used onomatopoeic (*) Quechua [KETCH-wah] words in the first part of a trilogy based on the Tristan legend, a song cycle called Harawi. This composer used the phrases “the time that runs” and “the play of life and death” to translate the two Sanskrit words in the title of his Turangalîla-Symphonie. For 10 points, name this French composer of Quartet for the End of Time.","formatted_answer":"Olivier <b><u>Messiaen<\/b><\/u> [or Olivier Eugène Prosper Charles <b><u>Messiaen<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Olivier <b><u>Messiaen<\/b><\/u> [or Olivier Eugène Prosper Charles <b><u>Messiaen<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"In this region, to “pank” something means to make it compact by patting it down, such as snow. A 1959 film shot in this region was one of the first Hollywood films to use words like “sperm,” “rape,” and “climax” in the sexual sense. That film, which was partly shot in this region’s city of Ishpeming, is Anatomy of a Murder. This region’s distinctive vocabulary, including the exclamation “Holy (*) wah,” is showcased in the Jeff Daniels movie Escanaba in da Moonlight. Residents of this region refer to people to their south as “trolls,” because those people live below the Mackinac [MAK-in-aw] Bridge. People from this region are known as “Yoopers.” For 10 points, name this northern portion of Michigan.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Upper Peninsula<\/b><\/u> of Michigan [or the <b><u>U.P.<\/b><\/u>; prompt on <u>Upper Michigan<\/u>; prompt on <u>Northern Michigan<\/u>; prompt on <u>Michigan<\/u> or the American <u>Midwest<\/u> before “trolls”]","answer":"<b><u>Upper Peninsula<\/b><\/u> of Michigan [or the <b><u>U.P.<\/b><\/u>; prompt on Upper Michigan; prompt on Northern Michigan; prompt on Michigan or the American Midwest before “trolls”]","category":"Geography","subcategory":"Geography","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"One of these works created by Pop Momand is the origin of the idiom “keeping up with the Joneses.” In one of these works, slang words are often written on the oversized shirt worn by Mickey Dugan, a character created by Richard F. Outcault. A 1993 book titled for these works defines the term “closure” as “observing the parts but perceiving the whole.” The words “poindexter” and (*) “milquetoast” both derive from characters in these works. Words like “briffits,” “plewds,” and “grawlixes” refer to symbols used in these works, according to a lexicon written by Mort Walker. The word “thagomizers,” meaning the spikes on a stegosaurus’s tail, was coined in one of these works by Gary Larson. For 10 points, name these works that often enclose dialogue in speech bubbles.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>comic<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>cartoon<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>comic<\/b><\/u> strips or <b><u>comic<\/b><\/u> books or Understanding <b><u>Comics<\/b><\/u>; do not accept or prompt on “graphic novels”]","answer":"<b><u>comic<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>cartoon<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>comic<\/b><\/u> strips or <b><u>comic<\/b><\/u> books or Understanding <b><u>Comics<\/b><\/u>; do not accept or prompt on “graphic novels”]","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"A text written in 2003 by a TV host honored what is probably the most famous instance of this activity, which took place in 1857 and was won by Klemens von Metternich. In a book named after this activity, the lines “void the words, void the silence” are followed by four diagrams of the human vocal tract. That book named after this activity has nine chapters titled for the nine Muses, and discusses women like Joan of Arc and (*) Yu Gwan-sun. Theresa Hak Kyung Cha’s magnum opus is titled for this activity, whose difficulty derives partly from the fact that a single sound can often be spelled in many different ways in French. For 10 points, name this exercise commonly used in French language education, in which the student has to write down a text that is recited by a speaker.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>dictation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>dictée<\/b><\/u>; reject “reading”]","answer":"<b><u>dictation<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>dictée<\/b><\/u>; reject “reading”]","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"An essay titled for William Wetmore Story’s sculpture The Libyan Sibyl illustrates this person’s ability to “move and bear down a whole audience by a few simple words” with an anecdote in which this person asked a speaker at Faneuil Hall “Is God dead?” In an account published later than Marcus Robinson’s account, this person had to be reminded of the word “intellect” by an audience member. The fact that this person was born in (*) New York and spoke only Dutch until the age of 9 casts doubt on Frances Dana Barker Gage’s use of a stereotypical Southern dialect to render a speech that this woman delivered in Akron in 1851. For 10 points, name this abolitionist who delivered the “Ain’t I a Woman?” speech.","formatted_answer":"Sojourner <b><u>Truth<\/b><\/u> [or Isabella <b><u>Baumfree<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Sojourner <b><u>Truth<\/b><\/u> [or Isabella <b><u>Baumfree<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"David Testen rejects Jacob Barth’s theory that this non-English word was formed by metathesis [meh-TATH-uh-sis] or syncope [SINK-uh-pee] from the language’s negative particle. In the absence of this word, nunation [nun-AY-shun] applies to words that are not in the construct state. The end of this word assimilates to the following sound if the following sound is a (*) “sun letter” as opposed to a “moon letter.” This is the first word in the two-word common title of a 9th-century “compendious book on calculation by completion and balancing” whose title is the origin of the name for a branch of math. This word, which always appears prefixed to another word, is common to the etymologies of the English words “artichoke,” “azimuth,” “adobe,” and “algebra.” For 10 points, name this Arabic definite article.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>al-<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>el-<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>il-<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>l-<\/b><\/u>; prompt on the <u>definite article<\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>al-<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>el-<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>il-<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>l-<\/b><\/u>; prompt on the definite article]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Chemistry","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"This novel notes that a character’s life was “put in jeopardy by words” after mentioning that “unsteady uses of words” have “perplexed the clearest and most exalted understandings.” The narrator of this novel is so ashamed to write the word “zounds” that he delays it until the next chapter, which reveals that the exclamation was occasioned by a roasted chestnut falling into Phutatorius’s fly. This novel’s narrator says that, every time he uses the word (*) “nose,” it means “a nose, and nothing more or less.” Walter, the father of this novel’s title character, believes strongly in the power of good and bad names and chooses the auspicious name “Trismegistus” for him. For 10 points, name this digressive novel by Laurence Sterne.","formatted_answer":"The Life and Opinions of <b><u>Tristram Shandy<\/b><\/u>, Gentleman","answer":"The Life and Opinions of <b><u>Tristram Shandy<\/b><\/u>, Gentleman","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"James Evans was nicknamed “the man who made [this material] talk” because of the syllabic writing system that he used on this material. According to legend, the first message written in the Irish ogham [OG-um] alphabet was a warning to Lug [loo] written on this material, and the first ogham letter has a name referring to this material. The words “I am a wild beast” accompany one of the drawings made on this material by (*) Onfim, a boy living in Novgorod [NOHV-guh-rut] in the 13th century. This material, one variety of which is named for the fact that it peels off like paper, was used to make wiigwaasabak [weeg-WAH-suh-buck] scrolls by the Ojibwe, who also use this material to make wigwams and canoes. For 10 points, many early manuscripts were written on what material sourced from a tree?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>birch<\/b><\/u> <b><u>bark<\/b><\/u> [accept either underlined portion]","answer":"<b><u>birch<\/b><\/u> <b><u>bark<\/b><\/u> [accept either underlined portion]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"This word is the title of a book subtitled “The New Force in American Politics and Culture,” written by Ed Morales. In 2021, LULAC announced that they would drop this word from their official communications. Research by Mark Hugo Lopez found that this word, which was coined around 2004, became much more popular in the wake of an attack carried out by Omar (*) Mateen. In 2021, the Arizona representative Ruben Gallego [ROO-bun gye-EGG-oh] stated that he does not allow this word in official communications, and said that it is used to “appease white rich progressives.” According to a 2020 Pew Research Center survey, only 3% of Hispanics use this word to describe themselves. For 10 points, name this controversial gender-neutral word for people in the U.S. with Latin American roots.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Latinx<\/b><\/u> [rhymes with “Kleenex”] [reject similar words that don’t end in X]","answer":"<b><u>Latinx<\/b><\/u> [rhymes with “Kleenex”] [reject similar words that don’t end in X]","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"The letter “t” is prefixed to this word to distinguish the propositional attitudes of two uneducated people who utter the same sentence in the paper “Other Bodies” by Tyler Burge. An argument about the meaning of this word was introduced in the same paper as arguments about the words “aluminum” and “molybdenum” and the words “elm” and “beech.” A normal form description of this word including the markers “mass noun” and “natural kind” is given in the paper “The (*) Meaning of Meaning.” Two people named Oscar use this word to refer to different things in a thought experiment developed as an argument for semantic externalism by Hilary Putnam. For 10 points, the Twin Earth thought experiment imagines a world where what word refers to the compound “XYZ,” instead of “H2O?”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>water<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>water<\/b><\/u>","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"This scientist came up with the sentence “Squdgy [SKWUD-jee] fez, blank jimp crwth [crooth] vox,” which uses all 26 English letters exactly once in just six words. This person used the punny acronym THROBAC [“throwback”] as the name of a calculator that used Roman numerals. A 1948 paper by this scientist lists a series of increasingly accurate approximations of English, from a (*) zero-order approximation to a second-order word approximation. That paper by this scientist popularized the word “bit” in the computer science sense, and characterizes messages sent from sources to destinations in terms of concepts like redundancy and entropy. The paper “A Mathematical Theory of Communication” is by, for 10 points, what “father of information theory”?","formatted_answer":"Claude (Elwood) <b><u>Shannon<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Claude (Elwood) <b><u>Shannon<\/b><\/u>","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":2,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
